Nietzsche talking about the European state
of mind at the end of the 19th century, so
Nietzsche says: well, we’re in this terrible
situation, right?
God is dead, we’ve killed him, what does
that mean?
Well, we’ve taken our evolved metaphysics
which structures our moral viewpoint and undermined
it by rational criticism – peculiar move
philosophically because it was never established
on rational grounds anyways.
We’ve undermined it rationally and replaced
it with, well, nothing, nothing.
What’s the consequence of that?
Well, he outlines that here.
“Of what is great, one must either be silent
or speak with greatness.”
And you can think about this as a prophesy
on the events of World War I and World War
II and the Gulag archipelago and the 60 million
people dead in the Soviet Union and the whole
unfolding of 20th century history and the
great ideological battles that characterized
that unfolding.
So this is something Nietzsche sees coming
and knows why.
He says:
“of what is great, one must either be silent
or speak with greatness.
With greatness.
That means cynically and with innocence.
What I relate of the history of the next two
centuries, I describe what is coming, what
can no longer come differently.
The advent of nihilism, right, the belief
in nothing.
Our whole European culture is moving for some
time now with a tortured tension that’s
growing from decade to decade as towards a
catastrophe, restlessly, violently, headlong
like a river that wants to reach the end that
no longer reflects.
It’s afraid to reflect.
He that speaks here has conversely done nothing
so far but to reflect as a philosopher and
solitary by instinct who has found his advantage
in standing aside outside.
“
Why does the advent of nihilism become necessary?
Well, because the values we’ve had hitherto
thus draw their final consequence because
nihilism represents the ultimate logical conclusion
of our great values and ideals because we
must experience nihilism before we can find
out what value these values really have.
We require at some time new values.
Nihilism stands at the door whence comes this
uncanniest of all guests.
Nihilism, right?
Your beliefs are undermined once, what’s
the consequence of that?
Well, one consequence is the belief is undermined.
The other consequence is more metaphysical,
which is: fooled once, you no longer have
the belief.
But maybe it’s even worse than that because
human beings can generalize.
Fooled once, you never have any, you no longer
have any belief in beliefs,
which means you say something like this: I
don’t care what you think, doesn’t matter
what you think, the world is such a terrible
place that no interpretation whatsoever can
possibly suffice.
That’s nihilism.
No meaning system whatsoever can possibly
suffice.
Well, what’s the flaw?
Well, the flaw is: well of course no system
of coherent belief can suffice because most
of the world’s transcendent.
You can’t encapsulate everything that is,
in your sphere of belief
and what you might say then is that if you
ever believe that what you believe is what
should support you, the facts you know say,
or the interpretation you place on the world,
then your faith is badly misplaced.
You don't believe in what you believe, you
believe in something that’s deeper than
that
And so then you see what’s wrong with Tolstoy,
right, and Tolstoy’s story and Tolstoy says,
accounting for his collapse in the stability
of Christian belief,
he said: this all happened, this collapse
of my belief, when I was not yet 50 years
old.
I should have been considered a completely
happy man.
I had a good, loving, beloved wife, fine children
and a large estate growing and expanding without
any effort on my part.
I was respected by friends and acquaintances,
praised by strangers and could claim a certain
renown.
I was not physically nor mentally unhealthy.
On the contrary, I enjoyed a physical and
mental vigour I had rarely encountered among
others my age.
I could keep up with the peasants working
in the fields and work eight and ten hours
at a stretch without suffering any after-effects
from the strain.
And in such a state of affairs, I came to
a point where I could not live and even though
I feared death, I had to employ ruses against
myself to keep from committing suicide.
It was as though I had lived a little, wandered
a little until I came to a precipice and I
clearly saw that there was nothing ahead except
ruin.
And there was no stopping or turning back,
no closing my eyes so that I would not see
that there was nothing ahead except the deception
of life and of happiness and of the reality
of suffering and death, of complete annihilation.
I grew sick of life.
Some irresistible force was leading me to
somehow get rid of it.
this thought was such a temptation that I
had to use cunning against myself in order
not to go through with it.
And there I was, a fortunate man carrying
a rope from my room where I was alone every
night as I undressed so that I would not hang
myself from the beam between the closets.
And I quit going hunting with a gun so that
I would not be too easily tempted to rid myself
of life.
I myself did not know what I wanted, was afraid
I struggled to get rid of it yet I hoped for
something from it.
My position was terrible.
I knew that I could find nothing in the way
of rational knowledge except a denial of life
and in faith I could find nothing except a
denial of reason.
And for me this was even more impossible than
a denial of life.
according to rational knowledge, it followed
that life is evil and people know it.
I described my spiritual condition to myself
in this way: my life is some kind of stupid
and evil practical joke that someone is playing
on me.
In spite of the fact that I did not acknowledge
the existence of any someone who might have
created me, the notion that someone brought
me into the world as a stupid and evil joke
seemed to be the most natural way to describe
my condition.
I could not be deceived.
All is vanity, happy is he who’s never been
born, death is better than life, we must rid
ourselves of life.
Having realized all the stupidity of the joke
that is being played on us, and seeing that
the blessings of the dead are greater than
those of the living and that it’s better
not to exist, the strong act and put an end
to this stupid joke and they use any means
of doing it – a rope around the neck, water,
a knife in the heart or a train.
Now the interesting thing about this, I think,
is first of all, a Russian wrote it; and second
of all, it was written in the late 1900s.
And even more particularly is that you note
that when the strong act, using a rope around
the neck, water, a knife in the heart and
a train, well, Tolstoy’s talking about suicide.
There’s no necessary reason to presume that
this should only be violence engendered against
the self, right?
If life is a stupid and evil joke, then what’s
stopping you from benevolently putting an
end to the suffering of others, right?
Benevolently in theory at least.
Well, you know that’s one perspective, right,
but then there’s always the perspective
of the lady who went to see the psychiatrist
in T.S.
Eliot’s poem, which is: well, if when your
eyes are open life appears as nothing but
suffering and pain to you, it could be that
that is how life is.
But it could also be that there’s something
wrong with the way that you’re looking at
the world.
And in some ways, that’s a much more humble
perspective, right, because the alternative
is: well, I know what’s going on and I just
look out there and there’s the world and
I’ve pretty much got it, like I know what
it means and what it means is pointless suffering
and pain and that’s my model and I don't
see any reason to question it.
But then the alternative is: well, wait a
second, there’s always the possibility that
I don’t know absolutely everything and this
final and horrible judgment that I’m placing
on the conditions of existence could conceivably
be misplaced, given the sort of presumptuousness
of the claim,
right?
I’m in a position to render final judgment
on the moral value of existence as such.
It seems to me reasonable to presume that
that’s not the kind of statement that you
should easily make
And I remember when George Bush launched his
most recent war, the initial terminology,
I think this was for the Afghanistan battle,
was: Operation Infinite Justice.
But he retracted that phrase after a number
of religious leaders objected to its kind
of presumptuousness –
which I thought was quite reasonable because
infinite justice is something that most people
should probably not hope for, right, because
you never know precisely what infinite justice
means
because it might just mean that every bloody
mistake you’ve ever made, you’re going
to pay for.
And I suppose that would be just as applicable
to George W. Bush as it would to anybody else
And then Milton again describes the development
of this adversarial spirit.
He says: first, pride, pride and worse, ambition,
threw me down.
That’s Satan’s lament when he’s in hell.
And Milton’s description of hell is extremely
interesting.
He said: the reason that hell is characterized
by its structure is not so much because of
its nature precisely, it’s because of its
distance from the good.
So the farther you are away, say, from what
constitutes the good, the more suffering is
endemic to that state.
So it’s the distance away from something
that constitutes the suffering.
And then Milton says: it’s very interesting
to do an analysis of Satan’s character and
the notion of hell per se because how in the
world can you reconcile the idea of a good
God with the notion of this continual suffering?
Milton says: well, Satan can step out of hell
in one moment, all he has to do is admit that
he was wrong.
And that’s the one thing that he will not
do under any circumstances whatsoever
So then we put one more twist on the story
and we say something like this:
OK, we already know that part of the reason
that people have belief systems is so that
they can structure their interactions with
the world.
It’s a tool box, say.
We’re playing a game, we share the rules,
that’s fine, we can cooperate with one another.
It could be other than it is but it’s the
way it is and it works for us, that’s fine.
There’s nothing absolute about it except
that a structure like that is necessary.
Now whenever there’s a threat to that shared
view of the world, well then we’re afraid
and for good reason and it’s not surprising
under those circumstances that we fight to
defend what we’ve made ours.
But then you say, say you adopt this perspective,
right, and it’s this vengeful desire to
destroy that extends beyond other individuals
and beyond society even to the structure of
experience as such.
And then you think: well, what’s the best
mask for that and how do these two processes
sort of interact?
And you think: well, the most efficient way
to do terrible things is to mask them with
the highest order of morality and that’s
precisely what the totalitarian does.
So that way, he gets to have his cake and
eat it too.
He’s perfectly well protected from apprehension
of the world because his belief system is
complete, plus his underground motivations,
which is this constant desire for revenge,
can find their expression within the totalitarian
structure and remain invisible even to himself.
So he can say to himself: well, the reason
I threw all those farmers out of their house
in 1920 and stole their soup and their food
and their grandmother’s blankets and everything
they’d worked to own was because I was building
a socialist paradise, right?
And it was a good thing for me to go into
that house and not a bad thing.
And as long as he believes that, or acts as
if he believes that, then he can look in the
mirror without screaming and there’s no
recognition whatsoever of precisely the sort
of game that he’s involved in, so he has
it both ways, right?
He can do everything terrible that he always
dreams of doing and consider himself not only
good but good even at a higher level than
the people that he was actually afflicting.
And of course, that’s just standard description
of what happened in the Soviet Union.
Nietzsche says, I love this, his definition
of morality, it’s the most cynical thing
Nietzsche ever said, I think: “the idiosyncrasy
of decadence with the ulterior motive of revenging
oneself against life successfully.
I attach value to this definition.”
He said: well, why be an ideologue?
Well, it’s a good way to simplify the world,
right?
It’s a procrustean bed, you just chop off
everything that doesn’t fit, then you don’t
have to think, right?
So that’s good because thinking is difficult
and it’s troublesome and it takes courage
and so forth to transform chaos into order
is no trivial matter.
And if it’s all ordered for you, well then
there’s really nothing left for you to do.
But then Nietzsche goes even below that.
He says: yeah, well there’s more to the
story than that, isn’t there?
It’s like once you got this little procrustean
bed all arranged for your enemies, then you
can allow your most base, vengeful instincts
full flow by just continually chopping people
so they fit.
And you do it, all the while saying: well,
it’s obviously the best thing that could
possibly be done.
And so then you look at Stalin, say, because
not everybody who’s adopted a vengeful tack
on existence is sort of like the archetype
of vengefulness or adversarial spirit.
But you get now and then the people like Stalin,
who are good counter-examples, say, to the
people like Gandhi.
And so Stalin’s very instructive and so
we could start by looking at what he did in
the Ukraine.
So at the end of 1929, the Kremlin decreed
that millions of peasants from individually
owned farms would be forced into agricultural
collectives or kolkhozes seen in the eyes
of the politburo as pliant providers of Soviet
agricultural needs.
In defiance of the facts, Soviet ideologists
hammered out an appropriate Marxist terminology
to explain what was going on.
Throughout grain-producing areas, it was said:
resistance to this scientific scheme was being
organized by so-called rich peasants or Gulaks.
With his customary brutality, therefore, Stalin
decreed the liquidation of the kulaks as a
class
Well, Stalin liked this idea of like group
guilt, that was a major theme for Stalin.
That meant I really didn’t have to pay attention
to you as an individual.
I could just decide if you were a doctor or
engineer or a kulak or a German or whatever
ethnic, racial or educational division happened
to characterize a particular target at the
time.
And it didn’t matter if you were guilty
as an individual.
That whole notion never even obtained.
It was class guilt that mattered and if you
were in one of those classes, well we’re
better without you.
And of course, the nature of the class just
changed constantly.
But it was a perfectly logical thing to think
if you believed in like historical determinism.
If your parents were rich bourgeois, what
was the probability that you’re going to
be a useful part of the workers’ collective?
It would be easier just to get rid of you
ahead of time so you didn’t cause too much
trouble.
So then you think about these kulaks, rich
peasants, well who were these people?
Like when we get down to the individual level?
So you go in a village, the village was full
of serfs, like not 40 years before, so these
are people just struggling out of the feudal
society,
right?
And you got some people in there who’ve
managed to be successful enough as farmers,
which is no easy thing, to like have a house
and maybe hire one person.
And you know maybe have a little extra food
in the larder and a few kind of material possessions.
So these are successful people and so you
could say: well, they’re the ones that actually
knew how to farm.
That’s one theory.
Or you could say: the reason they had all
this stuff was because they stole it from
all the other people, right?
And then you think: OK, so I march into town,
I’m a Soviet revolutionary and I say: hey,
guys, you know those rich people, they stole
everything they have from you.
And then you think: OK, which of you guys
is going to listen to that?
Well, it’s not going to be the sort of struggling
people just underneath them, who are really
trying to get ahead, right, because that’s
where they’re hoping to get.
It’s going to be the resentful and revengeful
few who think: well, the world’s fundamentally
unfair and it’s obvious that those sons
of bitches got what they want from stealing
it form me and here it turns out that if I
just go down the street and steal it back,
well, not only am I allowed to do that but,
according to this new emergent ideology, man,
that’s the best thing I could possibly do.
So then multiply that story by several million
participants and you have like the first five
years of the Soviet empire.
And so what do we have there?
The result was a catastrophic onslaught on
millions of peasant households.
At first, party activists and local officials,
read bullies, right, brutalized peasants,
forcing them to surrender their homesteads
and their possessions.
Deportations, arrests and killings soon followed
as terror generalized.
The violence mounted to full-scale rebellion
in various places, with regular troops engaged
for months.
For example, suppressing peasant uprisings.
Resistance took various forms, usually reflecting
the hopeless, desperate anguish of a doomed
population.
In the Ukraine, there were even women’s
rebellions, spontaneous uprisings of peasant
women who attacked the local Kolkhozes to
demand the return of confiscated farm products.
With a colossal impact on the Soviet economy,
peasants slaughtered their animals by the
millions rather than see them seized.
For two years, the fighting raged.
As the dreadful process of de-kulakization
continued, Stalin ordered a further assault
on the recalcitrant peasantry.
What Conquest calls the terror-famine of 1932.
Moscow, writes Conquest, it’s from a book
called The Harvest of Sorrow, knowingly decreed
grain procurements from the Ukraine and elsewhere
exceeding by far what the local population
could produce, right, which meant that everyone
who lived there was forced and ordered to
deliver more grain than they had ever grown.
Communist brigades roamed the countryside
forcing agriculturalists to disgorge the little
they had been able to produce under conditions
of severe dislocation.
Grain sat unused in state reserves while the
local population starved.
This is from Wisdom, apocryphal Biblical writings:
for the reasoned unsoundly saying to themselves:
short and sorrowful is our life and there
is no remedy when a man comes to his end and
no one has been known to return from Hades.
Because we were born by mere chance and hereafter
we shall be as though we had never been because
the breath in our nostrils is smoke and reason
a spark kindled by the beating of our hearts.
When it is extinguished, the body will turn
to ashes and the spirit will dissolve like
empty air.
Our name will be forgotten in time and no
one will remember our works.
Our life will pass away like the traces of
a cloud and be scattered like mist that is
chased by the rays of the sun and overcome
by its heat.
For our allotted time is the passing of a
shadow and there’s no return from our death
because it is sealed up and no one turns back.
So a piece of writing thousands of years old
and so Nietzsche says at the end of the 1900s:
well, rationality undermines our faith in
religion.
But we have a piece of writing from more than
2,000 years ago that says: look, what is it
about being alive?
It’s short and there’s nothing to it,
right?
Our thoughts are biologically produced and
when we die there’s nothing left.
Well, that’s a very modern thought yet it
was expressed thousands of years ago so you
know, I think, merely from observing that
that the crisis of faith that characterizes
modern society is a reflection of the permanent
crisis of faith that characterizes human beings.
and you say: well, what’s happening with
the totalitarian?
Well, the totalitarian is afraid of the unknown,
for good reason, I mean and he’s very interested
in sustaining his own belief structure.
And the combination of those two things, it
can start off trivially is that the more you’re
convinced that you have to maintain the stability
of your current belief structure, the more
afraid you are of anything that’s unknown.
And the more afraid you are of anything that’s
unknown, the less likely you are to go out
and explore.
Then the less likely you are to go out and
explore, the weaker you get because you stop
gather information.
And then the weaker you get, the more necessary
it is that you have to have this frame of
reference and it has to remain intact.
And this sort of thing starts to cycle and
cycle.
So you undermine your own sense of your own
autonomy and ability and you make yourself
more and more a rigid tool of the propagandistic
system.
And you more and more adopt a sense of enmity
towards anything you don’t understand.
And that’s a spiral that goes rapidly down
hill, right, rapidly into a state that’s
characterized by complete internal chaos
And I think that’s a good definition of
what is meant in metaphysical language by
hell, right?
Hell is a bottomless pit.
Why?
Well, I don’t care how bad things are for
you or around you, there’s always some bloody
thing you could do to make it worse, right?
There’s always some suffering you can extend
to others, there’s always some bit of stubbornness
or rejection that you can pull off that will
make your already terrible situation worse,
right?
So there’s no bottom and that seems to me
to be right.
If you do just a cursory historical analysis,
no matter what terrible account you can come
across with regards to, say, concentration
camp brutality, in some other book there’s
some worse story.
Like limited only by the absolute ends of
the most brutal form of imagination, all a
consequence, I think, of this process, right?
And you can’t really say what causes it
because on the one hand, there’s cowardice
and lack of faith, right?
Anything I don’t understand – cowardice,
pride and lack of faith.
Anything I don’t understand doesn’t exist,
plus I’m not the person to confront it anyways,
right?
That’s the lack of faith.
Each of those things feeds into the other
and it’s very difficult to say where it
starts.
And the thing that’s kind of interesting
about these self-referential processes is
that they don’t have to start dramatically.
Like the loop can start very, very small and
it picks up speed very, very rapidly.
So you imagine you’re speaking into a tape
recorder and the speaker’s on.
You get too close to the speaker with the
microphone and you get some feedback.
And if you bring the microphone a little closer,
the feedback develops more and more intensely.
It can blow up the whole system.
It doesn’t have to start dramatically to
move forward very, very rapidly.
And what that means, at least in principle,
is that even small mistakes anywhere along
this circle can start the development of precisely
this kind of spiral.
And so you say: well, people, do people need
to be abused to become totalitarian?
Well, and the answer to that is no because
everyone’s been abused sufficiently by some
occurrences in their life to justify taking
a negative tack on the nature of experience.
You say: well, how cowardly do you have to
be in order to run away from things?
And you think: well, not that cowardly because
under most circumstances your life is characterized
by sins of omission, right?
It’s there are things you left undone
and like just exactly how rigid do you want
your belief systems to be?
And you say: well, I like them to be stable
because without that stability, then I’m
terrified.
And then you can say: well, fair enough but
that’s all a sign of a kind of existential
weakness.
And then if social circumstances come around
and give your life a good tweak, say like
they did with the Germans prior to World War
II, you just never know what side you’re
going to end up on.
And so all these little tiny mistakes you
know, mistakes that I think are marked by
your own conscience, are precisely that, leads
you down this terrible path.
And if you think: well, no, that can’t be
right – well, then you have to remember
that in these processes, say, of de-kulakization
and the immense wave of death that characterized
the Soviet Union and Nazi Germany, most people
were involved.
And if they weren’t involved in direct acts
of commission, they were absolutely involved
in direct acts of omission, right?
They knew but they didn’t say anything.
Well, classically sins of commission are regarded
as much more evil, say, than sins of omission.
But I actually think that’s backwards.
The sins of omission are worse because every
time you walk away, I mean what do you do?
You walk away from a Nazi, what are you walking
away from?
Well, we know what you’re walking away from,
right?
If you’re walking away from a domain that’s
likely to expand into something that’s completely
undifferentiable from hell, and it’s no
wonder you walk away from that, but the fact
that you walk away from it makes it much more
likely that it’s going to happen
So then I think, to end this, something like
this.
We look for economic reasons to explain great
terrible acts, right?
We look for social reasons, we look for political
reasons but we have Nietzsche’s observation,
which is something like this:
I don’t care whether or not your life’s
been characterized by suffering and deprivation.
The mere fact of suffering and deprivation
does not allow you to draw a particular conclusion.
You can’t say that there’s a causal path
between economic deprivation, say, and the
rise of a totalitarian state because any event
is susceptible to multiple interpretations.
Well, how do these states come about?
Well, I think: well, we look for political
and economic and social reasons because that’s
the easiest place top look, right?
If you ratchet up the level of description
to social forces that are beyond your control,
then you never have to worry about what it
is that you’re doing or not doing that’s
actually causing this sort of thing.
But I think if you look at the historical
record, especially if you look at it from
a mythological perspective, the story is basically
clear and it goes something like this:
Every time you make a mistake that you know
is a mistake and you don’t fix it, the world
moves more towards that.
And it might be trivial, maybe, but it might
not be.
So you look at Adolf Eichmann, for example,
and he’s a little bureaucrat who planned
the Final Solution and you find out he’s
just a little ratty guy, right?
You see him in a bar, you don’t even notice
him, he’s a negligible nobody.
But he’s the guy who planned the Final Solution.
He was a normal person, I mean maybe even
slightly less than normal, right?
He is no monster, he wasn’t the sort of
person you’d remark on if you saw him.
Precisely the opposite: invisible, quiet,
unassuming, presuming no doubt, at least until
he was arrested, that he was just doing what
he was told and that was just fine.